Noah Scovell Papers, 1783-1819
Connecticut Historical Society
Noah Scovell Papers
1783-1819
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Scovell, Noah (1759-1821)
1 linear foot (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
Noah Scovell was born in 1759 in Potapogue Parish, Saybrook, Connecticut, the son of William and Ruth Webb Scovell. Noah married Desire Pratt (1759-1819) of Essex and they raised five children, namely Noah (b. 1781), Lewis (1783-1806), Sebra or Seabury (1785-1805), Amos (1787-1852) and Maria (1789-1834). Noah was a merchant and shipbuilder. His vessels primarily traded in the West Indies and along the Eastern seaboard. They included the Dolphin (Brig), Friendship (Brig), Patty and Julia (Ship) and Fairplay (Schooner). Between 1810-1812, he and his son Noah experimented with importing Merino sheep from Spain. Son Noah moved to New York to carry on the merchant trade and assist his father.
Scope and Content
This collection is gathered from several purchased sets of papers. The bulk of the collection, containing Scovell’s correspondence, financial records and papers pertaining to the Brig Dolphin, was purchased in one group. Additional papers, many relating to other ships owned and/or captained by Scovell, came from other collections. The papers have been arranged chronologically.
The first nine folders contain letters written to Mr. Scovell between 1785 and 1819, with an additional folder for undated correspondence. The majority of these letters are about business matters, shipping opportunities and questions about purchases. Also included are family letters and letters written to Noah Scovell, Jr. There are also five letters, each transcribed in pencil, about a black girl owned by Mr. Scovell named Violet. In 1802 she ran away, in 1803 he considered selling her, and in 1808 he wrote his son to tell him of her death.
Included in the collection are a handful of letters that do not appear to involve either Noah Scovell or his son. One, dated 1823, is addressed to Mr. Luther Holey and is from his son. Another, dated 1802, is an address from the Farmington town committee. Two more, from 1832, are addressed to Mr. John Slater.
Eight folders contain financial records dated between 1783 and 1811, plus many undated papers and some written in French. Many of these are connected with Scovell’s shipping concerns. There are also bills of lading and other papers for many of the ships Scovell owned or captained, including the Caroline, the Friendship, the Fairplay and the Patty and Julia.
There are also nine folders containing papers relating to the Brig Dolphin. Included are letters to Scovell about the ship, general financial records, and voyage accounts from 1786 to 1789. There is also a “minet book” with records relating to a single voyage of the Dolphin.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Scovell, Noah, 1759-1821.; Scovell, Noah, b. 1781.
Subjects
Dolphin (Brig).; Fairplay (Schooner).; Friendship (Brig).; Patty & Julia (Ship).; Coastwise shipping.; Merchant ships --Connecticut --Saybrook.; Ship captains --Connecticut --Saybrook.; Saybrook (Conn.) --History --Sources.; West Indies.
Contents:
- Papers
  - Correspondence, 1785-1789 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1790-1793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1794-1795 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1796-1797 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1799-1801 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1802-1804 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1805-1807 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1808-1819 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family correspondence (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Noah Scovell, Jr. correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Account of runaway black girl named Violet (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Non-Scovell family correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financial records, 1783-1787 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial records, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial records, 1789-1790 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial records, 1791-1799 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Financial Records, 1800-1811 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Financial records, in French (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bills of lading (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ships’ papers (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brig Dolphin, correspondence (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Brig Dolphin, general financial (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Brig Dolphin, “Minet Book”, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brig Dolphin, voyage accounts, 1786-1787 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brig Dolphin, voyage accounts, 1788, 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Brig Dolphin, voyage accounts, 1788, 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brig Dolphin, voyage accounts, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 32)